Copeland MacClintock Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Copeland MacClintock Archives
1963-2014
IPAR.001246
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
1
The achrives of Copeland MacClintock encompassing his career at Yale. These include maps, field notebooks, biographical information, and an extensive oral history.
MacClintock, Copeland
Biographical Sketch
MacClintock received his MA from the University of Wyoming in 1957. He received his PhD from the University of California, Berkeley in 1964. He came to the Peabody in 1963 and retired in 2010. Since then he has regularly volunteered his time and institutional memory to the division of Invertebrate Paleontology. His research focuses on shell microstructure within the Mollusca, though he also has an extensive personal knowledge of the invertbrate paleontology collections at the Peabody.
Description of the Material
Includes field notes, locality information and topographic maps pertaining to Cope's personal collection. Also includes a series of recordings about the history of the Peabody Museum, transcripts of staff stories and retirement speeches.
Connecticut; Massachusetts; USA; Field notebooks; Field notebooks; Maps; Locality information; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Maps, Series I
  - Massachusetts., 001249
    - Topographic map. Provincetown, MA 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic. [transferred to Invertebrate Zoology Division, Aug. 2011], 1958; 001889
    - Topographic map. Wellfleet, MA 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic. [transferred to Invertebrate Zoology Division, Aug. 2011], 1958; 001890
    - Topographic map. Chatham, MA 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic. [transferred to Invertebrate Zoology Division, Aug. 2011], 1961; 001891
    - Topographic map. Hyannis, MA 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1961; 001892
- Field Notes, Series II
  - Field Notes., 001251
    - Field notes. Field notes from 1959 class trip to Paleozoic of Ward Mt, Egan Range, White Pine County, Nevada, 000962
    - Field notes. Field notes for collections of Recent bivalves: Massachusetts. [transferred to Invertebrate Zoology Division, Aug. 2011 by C. MacC.], 1965; 000298
    - Field notes. Field notebook, & other notes; Milford, Connecticut; Massachusettes, 1967; 000674
    - Field notes. Field notebook, field maps, missing concs., fossil counts, original MS, review comments, font change; Holocene, Post-glacial, Connecticut (West Haven, East Haven, Milford); Massachusetts (Cape Cod). 1968, 1999, 000716
    - Field notes. field notes and maps for C. MacClintock, 1957, University of Wyoming Masters thesis, Upper Part of Morrison Formation and Cloverly Formation, Southeastern Big Horn Mountains, Wyoming, 000959
    - Locality information. Notes on bivalve collections: Connecticut, Massachusetts. 1966, 1968; GB # card catalog, 000213
    - Locality information. Notebook for collections of Recent bivalves: Massachusetts. 1966, 1967, 000299
  - Locality Information., 001250
    - Catalog of localities. Catalog of Copeland MacClintock collecting localities, 1962-1963 (M-100 to M-122), 000961
    - Locality information. Location map of fossil localities: Austria., 1968; 000176
    - Locality information. locality information (notes and maps): New Jersey., 1992; 000389
    - Locality information. locality information: New Jersey, 1993; 000420
    - Locality information. Locality information, Lobster Lake, Maine, Silurian., 2004; 000789
    - Locality information. locality information, California, Oakland, Tertiary, Squilla, 000800
    - Locality information. Locality information & map for Holocene concretions, Prospect Beach, West Haven, Connecticut, 000965
- Miscellaneous, Series III
  - Accession Project., 001253
    - Miscellaneous. Accession project for whole IP collection done by C. MacClintock about 1987, 000818
  - Manuscripts., 003088
    - Manuscript for Malacologia reviewed by Cope MacClintock. Differenciation des genres Homalocantha (Morch), Jaton (Pusch) & Maxwellia (J. L. Baily, Jr.) (Gasteropodes Prosobranches, fam. Muricidae) au moyen de la structure microscopique et de la nature mineralogique de leur coquille. by Michel Petitjean., 003089
  - Miscellaneous., 003093
    - Friends of the Gastropods newsletters from 1982 and 1983., 003094
- Biographical Information and Memorabilia, Series IV
  - Staff Retirement Speeches., 001326
    - Dolf Seilacher. Adolf Seilacher Dinner, December 8, 2009 (on the occasion of his second retirement - this time from Yale) and two poems read on this occasion - "Ode to a Trilobite" by T. A. Conrad, "Part Two" by C. MacClintock, 001330
    - John H. Ostrom. Limericks for John H. Ostrom on the occasion of retirement supper at the Quinnipiac Club - February 22, 1994, 001327
  - Staff Stories and Reminiscences., 001328
    - John H. Ostrom. How John Ostrom got into paleontology (as told to Cope MacClintock, March 23, 2000), 001329
    - Karl M. Waage. Memorial Service for Karl M. Waage (Cope's words of remembrance - March 17, 2000), 17 Mar 2000; 001331
    - Karl M. Waage. poems and stories as recorded by C. MacClintock, 1937-1994; 001332
- Oral History, Series V
  - Activities in Retirement., 001381
    - Geology Hikes and Kiosks. Cope's work on geology kiosks for East Rock Park and leading geology hikes, 001383
    - Miscellaneous. Cope's research into glacial striae and tornado tree fall mapping. Also his love of turtles, tennis. The Peabody Motto., 001384
    - Research Papers. Dolf Seilacher's Morphodynamics Paper and the Gibbon Ammonite., 001382
  - Miscellaneous., 001356
    - Bison Diorama Location. Bison diorama location and collaboration with Michael Coe to find it., 001376
    - Bog Diorama Location., 001375
    - Forest Margin Diorama Location., 001374
    - John Cisne Puns. Cope telling of a John Cisne pun regarding ammonites. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001359
    - Powerpoint Presentations. Cope's view on powerpoint presentations. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001357
    - Shore Diorama Location., 001373
    - Twenhofel Notebooks. Cope's plea for the return of the Twenhofel notebooks. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001358
  - Notable Events. Cope MacClintock's recollections of various notable events., 001336
    - Aetosaurus. Cope's telling of rediscovering the collecting locality for Aetosaurus. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001353
    - Antietam. Cope's telling of his side trip to Antietam during a trip to North Carolina. Includes a poem. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001351
    - Bingham Lab Custodian. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001347
    - Black Panther Trial. Peabody''s response to the Black Panther trial and the May Day riots., 001370
    - Blizzard of 1978. Cope MacClintock's remembrances of the Blizzard of 1978. Recorded 28 Feb 2013., 001345
    - Edward D. Cope Skull. Cope's telling of National Geographic bringing E.D. Cope's skull to the Peabody Museum for a documentary on the Bone Wars. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001354
    - Egypt Exhibit Opening. Egypt exhibit opening and Hosne Mubarack. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001350
    - Gorilla Story. Paul Whitehead's gorilla. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001348
    - Great Fault Earthquake. Cope's telling of the Great Fault earthquake of Oct. 1987. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001355
    - J. Brooks Knight Collections. Cope's mistake in regards to the J. Brooks Knight LaBette Shale collections., 001379
    - Jurassic Park. Seeing Jurassic Park with John Ostrom and Rudy Zallinger., 001380
    - Mineral Hall Photographs. Cope's telling of taking photographs for the Mineral Hall of road cuts along Route 9. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001349
    - Museum Fumigation., 001371
    - Prague. Cope MacClintock's remembrances of his trip to Prague in Aug 1968. Warsaw Pact invasion. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001346
    - Princeton Collections. Cope's role in organizing and transporting the Princeton Vertebrate Paleontology collections to the Peabody., 001372
    - SPNHC 2012 Field Trip. Cope's favorite field trip. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001352
  - Paper Documents. Paper Documents used by Cope for his oral history., 002417
    - Paper Documents. Paper Documents used by Cope for his oral history., 002418
  - People. Cope MacClintock's recollections of various individuals., 001335
    - Adolf Seilacher. Cope MacClintock's remembrances of Adolf Seilacher. Recorded 28 Feb 2013., 001341
    - Adolf Seilacher. Cope MacClintock's remembrances of Adolf Seilacher. Recorded 28 Feb 2013., 001342
    - Arthur Bischoff., 001367
    - Carl Dunbar & Dorcas MacClintock. Cope MacClintock's remembrances of his wife, Dorcas and also of Carl Dunbar. Recorded 28 Feb 2013., 001339
    - Carl Dunbar & Karl Waage. Cope's reading a letter from Carl Dunbar to Karl Waage. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001361
    - Charles Remington. Charles Remington and the fossil insect collections. Plus how Charles Remington got his middle name., 001363
    - Charles Sibley & Derek Price., 001365
    - Elwyn Simons. A story of Elwyn Simons visiting John Ostrom in the field., 001362
    - George Evelyn Hutchinson & Cornelius Osgood. Cope MacClintock's remembrances of George Evelyn Hutchinson, Halley's Comet and Cornelius Osgood. Recorded 28 Feb 2013., 001344
    - John Ostrom. Cope MacClintock's remembrances of John Ostrom. Recorded 28 Feb 2013., 001340
    - Karl Waage and Karl Turekian. Karl Waage and Karl Turekian at Little Bighorn Battlefield., 001385
    - Karl Waage. Cope MacClintock's remembrances of Karl Waage. Recorded 28 Feb 2013., 001338
    - Leo Pospisil., 001364
    - Malcolm Thorpe & Percy Morris., 001366
    - Nick Bellentoni. P-40 crash site investigation., 001369
    - Richard F. Flint & Reuben J. Ross. Cope's telling of Richard Flint & Reuben Ross wearing their military uniforms in lectures. Recorded 07 Mar 2013., 001360
    - Rudolph F. Zallinger. Cope MacClintock's remembrances of Rudolph F. Zallinger. Recorded 28 Feb 2013., 001343
    - Russell (Tim) White. Story of Cope working with Russell White and a trip to New Mexico, 001368
  - Time at the Peabody Museum. Cope MacClintock's history at the Peabody Museum., 001334
    - Time at the Peabody Museum. Cope MacClintock's oral history of his time at the Peabody Museum. Recorded 28 Feb 2013., 001337